Guide to the Plácido Vega Papers, 1855-1864
Department of Special Collections
- (October, 1860) (Box 4, Folder 57)
  Letters to Plácido Vega from Luis Tirado, M. Delgado, A. Rosales, E. Félix, R. Félix y Buelna, J. Álvarez, I. Zaragoza, I. Vallarta, P. Ogazón (campaign for Guadalajara); from Q. Douglas, Pesquiera (reference to Yaquis); from J. García Morales, J. Mugarrieta, J. J. Tostado, J. Gago, B. Orrantia, Jesús Vega, Fortino León, Camilo Vega, Ubano Gómez, A. Barreto, others. Letters from P. Vega to I. Zaragoza, I. Vallarta, Fortino León, P. Ogazón, A. Aragón, Juan García, E. Huerta, A. Rosales, M. Marquez, other military officers, officials, supporters. Official documents, records pertaining to Espinal; statement concerning action by M. Márquez; statement concerning rout of Spaniard Domingo Cajen. List of men wounded or killed during action.
- (November, 1860) (Box 4, Folder 58)
  Letters to Plácido Vega from Urbano Gómez, military officers (rout of Cajen); from M. Romero, R. Corona, Pesquiera, M. Delgado, Luis Tostado, J. de la Vega, F. Aragón, E. Félix, Carlos Vega, Camilo Vega, Bulnes, P. Blancarte, others. Letters from Plácido Vega to A. Herrera, E. Huerta, A. Rojas, others.
- (November, 1860) (Box 4, Folder 59)
  Letters to Plácido Vega from R. Félix y Buelna, I. González, P. Blancarte, A. Aragón, other military officers, supporters; from Benito Juárez (developments, elections, plans). Letters from Plácido Vega to Urbano Gómez (rout of Cajen); to P. Ogazón, J. González Ortega, M. Doblado, R. Corona, S. Degollado, other military officers, supporters.
- (December, 1860) (Box 4, Folder 60)
  Letters to Plácido Vega from R. Félix y Buelna, M. Delgado, L. Tostado, M. Romero, R. Corona (including financial statement); from M. Márquez, P. Orgazón A. Rosales, F. Aragón, C. Peña, A. Aragón, P. Blancarte (reference to defeat of Miramon); from A. Vega. Letters from Plácido Vega to M. Márquez, Pesquiera, L. Tostado, others.
- (December, 1860) (Box 4, Folder 61)
  Letters to Plácido Vega from military officers, supporters; from I. Zaragoza (preparation for action near San Miguel); from M. Márquez, A. Vega, E. Félix, Jesús Vega, P. Blancarte, J. M. Bulnes, R. Corona, C. Peña, A. Rosales, L. Tostado, M. Romero, M. Doblado, J. Gonzalez Ortega (defeat of General Berriozábal at Toluca); from Fortino León, Mugarrieta. Copies of letters sent by Mugarrieta to Gerónimo Amador in Baja California. Letters from Plácido Vega to I. Zaragoza, lesser military officers, officials, supporters.
- (January, 1861) (Box 4, Folder 62)
  Letters to Plácido Vega from L. Tostado (including list of medicines needed for soldiers stationed at Rosario during January); from Bulnes, Aragón (political, military matters; intentions of W. MacKintosh); from Buelna, F. Malcampo (financial), F. Álvarez (reference to capture of capital, rout of Miramon, and pending arrival of President in capital; support of Joarez); from Patoni, E. Huerta (military and political matters; reference to elections and to Juárez); from Zaragoza, Blancarte. Letters from Plácido Vega to Bulnes, Aragón, Tostado.
- (February - April, 1861) (Box 4, Folder 63)
  Documents signed by Fortino León, others, granting Plácido Vega official leave as governor of Sinaloa for specific period, to permit Vega to go to Guadalajara. Proclamation by Plácido Vega to inhabitants of Sinaloa, declaring Fortino León to serve as governor in his absence. Letters to Plácido Vega from J. González Ortega (political, military matters: suspicions concerning Doblado); from Urbano Lassepas (political situation in capital; notes on government officials); from Fortino León, P. Ogazón, Pesquiera (pacification of Yaquis, Mayos); from Benito Juárez (reference to latter's arrival in capital); from I. Ramirez, others. Letter from Plácido Vega to Fortino León; reports by P. Ogazón.
- (February, 1861) (Box 5, Folder 64)
  Letters to Plácido Vega from military officers, supporters; from Juan de Dios Robles Martínez, informing Plácido Vega of new cabinet post appointments in capital; from M. Carreaga, José L. Padilla, C. Monzón, Luis Tirado, E. Norton, J. Mugarrieta, J. García Morales.
- (March, 1861) (Box 5, Folder 65)
  Letters to Plácido Vega from I. Zaragoza, Fortino León, J. Arzapalo, Urbano Gómez, R. Bonilla, military officers. Financial statement sent by G. Miller. Complaint by A. Herrera; reply from Placido Vega. Letters from Plácido Vega to I. Zaragoza, Fortino León, J. Arzapalo.
- (April, 1861) (Box 5, Folder 66)
  Letters to Plácido Vega from R. Félix y Buelna, Captain S. Bissell, J. Sepúlveda, J. González Ortega (political); from Mugarrieta (reference to deteriorating political situation); from Patoni (activities of Pablo Lagarma); from J. García Morales, Fortino León, I. Zaragoza. Letters from Plácido Vega to Benito Juárez, (situation in Sonora, northern states). Copy of letter sent to President Lincoln in Washington, expressing gratitude for services rendered by Simon Bissell, captain of ship Cezane (?)
- (May, 1861) (Box 5, Folder 67)
  Note to Plácido Vega from governor of Nuevo León and Coahuila; letters from supporters, military officers; from F. Cortés, J. Sepulveda, M. Delgado (Lagarma, etc.). Copy of letter sent by Plácido Vega to Benito Juárez Rosales and Lagarma).
- (April - June, 1861) (Box 5, Folder 68)
  List of medicines for battalion; reports by Miguel Gomez. Letters to Plácido Vega from supporters (requests for interviews, appointments, etc.). Reports by Romero, Q. Douglas, Letters to Plácido Vega from Fortino León, J. Gonzalez Ortega, I. Zaragoza, P. Ogazón, Benito Juárez, M. Maquez, Juan Alvarez (political); from Pesquiera (Yaquis, Mayos; Juárez); from R. Félix y Buelna, F. Cortés, L. Tirado, J. Herrera, U. Lassepas. Letters from Plácido Vega to J. González Ortega, Fortino León, I. Zaragoza, P. Ogazón.
- (July, 1861) (Box 5, Folder 69)
  Letters to Plácido Vega from General Uraga, R. Félix y Buelna (military, administrative matters); from P. Blancarte, J. Río, L. Tostado, I. Zaragoza, (recommendations for appointments); from Benito Juárez (judicial, political matters; personnel); from B. Sánchez, F. Ocampo, Riveroli, (desire of northern states to secede); from M. Márquez, P. Ogazón (political); from J. Rojas, F. Arellano, Fortino León (desertion of battalion at Zacatecas); from others.
- (July, August, 1861) (Box 5, Folder 70)
  Letters to Plácido Vega from M. Márquez, L. Tostado, Benito Juárez (political appointments); from Fortino León (reference to action at Fuerte); from officials at port of Mazatlán, others. Letters from Plácido Vega to M. Márquez, P. Orgazón, M. Doblado, Benito Juárez (political appointments).
- (August, 1861) (Box 5, Folder 71)
  Letters to Placido Vega from C. Pena (military report); from Juan Kelly, J. Castaneda, I. Comonfort, upon latter's return to Mexico. Reports from military officers. Reply from M. Márquez to letter from Plácido Vega. Letters from Plácido Vega to I. Comonfort, Fortino León, F. Cortés. Notes to M. Márquez, demanding explanation of recent proceedings; giving orders.
- (August, September, 1861) (Box 5, Folder 72)
  Letters to Plácido Vega from P. Pinzón, C. Palomares, B. Peraza, I. Pesquiera, Jesús Vega (military developments); from Camilo Vega (including inventory or list of clothing, supplies on hand); from M. Márquez, J. Arzapalo. P. Blancarte, J. García Morales, R. Félix y Buelna (military matters); from other military officers and from local officials on such matters as outcome of elections, etc.; from Miguel Castro, J. J. Tostado, F. Flórez, C. Peña, F. Ocampo, Fortino León, others. Lists of officers for First Battalion of Sinaloa, company by company. Letters from officials at customs house, port officials at Mazatlan; from relatives.
- (October, 1861) (Box 6, Folder 73)
  Samples of script sent to Placido Vega. Papers from prefecture of district of Fuerte: arms acquired; recommendations concerning prisoner held; inventory, or list of arms on hand; financial statement by B. Peraza, etc. Instructions to R. Félix y Buelna from Plácido Vega. Reports from A. Castro, R. Félix y Buelna; notes and instructions sent by Plácido Vega to authorities at Fuerte, to prefects at Guaymas, Sinaloa, Mccorito, etc. Intelligence received by Plácido Vega concerning activities of Antonio Esteves. Letters to Plácido Vega from General Uraga (inevitability of war with France; commentary on situation); from J. García Morales, B. Peraza (December, 1861 and January, 1862), concerning action relating to Márquez. Letters to Plácido Vega from Fortino León, others, imparting intelligence concerning activities of Meza and Márquez.
- (October, 1861) (Box 6, Folder 74)
  Records concerning ship Carmelita; letters imparting information about other vessels. Instructions issued by Plácido Vega; records of information received by Plácido Vega from J. García Morales, others (reference to Juan Mott, to ship Isaac, etc.). Letters to Plácido Vega from L. Tostado, M. Márquez, others. Copy of information given L. Tostado by M. Márquez; statement by J. García Morales, other papers.
- (October, 1861) (Box 6, Folder 75)
  Letters to Plácido Vega from F. Cortés, I. Pesquiera (Yaquis and Mayos); from military officers, officials imparting information concerning defeat of Esteves; from R. Félix y Buelna (factional differences, Esteves, Yaquis and Mayos, prisoner, J.M.Almada); from Bissell, M. Márques.
- (November, 1861) (Box 6, Folder 76)
  Note from Pesquiera; papers from prefect of district of Alamos; documents made out by P. Pinzón, N. Moreno, concerning prisoners, etc. Letters to Plácido Vega from C. Palomares, Pesquiera, concerning prisoners J. Almada, M. Ibarra, S. Álvarez). Documents signed by Plácido Vega; other papers relating to prisoners; official orders concerning Esteves, instructions, etc.
- (November, 1861) (Box 6, Folder 77)
  Notes to Plácido Vega from F. Félix, others. Reports from officials, supporters; letters to Plácido Vega from Alejandro Santa Cruz, F. Cortés, M. Márquez, J. García Morales, R. Félix y Buelna, I. Pesquiera. List of arms taken from enemy; documents signed by Pesquiera.
- (November, 1861) (Box 6, Folder 78)
  Letters to Pacido Vega from E. Lamberg (military matters, plans); from P. Ogazón (Yaquis, Mayos); from M. Zerón (political, military); from Blancarte, William Hill, J. Castañeda, J. Mugarrieta (reference to ship Pánama); from Fortino León, M. Márquez. Letters from Plácido Vega to Blancarte, Hill. Statement of sale of boat Álamos sent by W. Hill.
- (December, 1861) (Box 6, Folder 79)
  Statements by I. Pesquiera concerning Almada. Inventory of items on hand for army. Financial statement. Official statement pertaining to capture of prisoners. Statement from deputy to legislature from district of Urique in state of Chihuahua. Statement by Martín Salida giving account of meeting of government officials from Sonora and Sinaloa in Mazatlán. Statement by Plácido Vega stipulating latter's need to return to Mazatlán. Explanation by J. García Morales of military decision (Mayos); note from Plácido Vega to R. Félix y Buelna informing latter of plans and of Morales' decision. Letters to Plácido Vega from Q. Douglas (reference to political, financial, military matters); from M. Márquez, L. Tostado (reference to ship Pánama, military developments, debts); from J. García Morales, E. Lamberg (military matters). Official statement of promotion of Ezquiel Ávilez to rank of captain. Letters from Plácido Vega to Q. Douglas.
- (January, 1862) (Box 7, Folder 80)
  Letters to Plácido Vega from E. Buelna, F. Tirado, Jesús Vega (reference to Tacubaya, to matters in Sonora); from A. Aragón, Q. Douglas, J García Morales J. Sepúlveda, A. Rojas, C. Palomares (reference to seizure of Veracruz; plans). Latters from other officials, supporters; from Urbano Gómez, J. de Dios Robles Martínez, P. Ogazón (Alicia); from I. Pesquiera (Esteves and accomplices; copy of letter sent Benito Juárez enclosed); from P. Blancarte, others. Report from J. Arzapalo; F. Tirado. Letters from Plácido Vega to J. Arzapalo, I. Pesquiera (Esteves and accomplices; action to be taken); to J. de Dios Robles Martínez, P. Ogazón (Alicia, other matters); to J. García Morales, Q. Douglas, F. Tirado, L. Tostado. Statements from prefect of district of El Fuerte, statements by officials concerning ships Mutine and Anáhauc, etc.
- (January, February, 1862) (Box 7, Folder 81)
  Letter to Plácido Vega from a secretary of President Lincoln's acknowledging receipt of letter from Plácido Vega expressing appreciation for services rendered by Bissel in aiding Mexicans to suppress Indian disturbances in North. Translation of above letter into Spanish. Official statements by P. Ogazón in regard to ship Anáhauc and other matters. Authorization by treasurer for payment of sums. Lists of officials of various states, districts, divisions of army, etc. Copy of letter to Benito Juárez from Fortino León concerning ships Pánama and República, and matter of foreign claims (February, 1862). Letters from Plácido Vega to Benito Juárez on same subject, on P. Ogazón's campaign in Alicia, and on matter of Esquivel. Letter to Plácido Vega from Benito Juárez dated August, 1861 and concerning political, military matters. Letters to Plácido Vega from Blancarte, R. Herrera, others (January, 1862).
- (February, 1862) (Box 7, Folder 82)
  Statements by treasurer, by J. García Morales; reports by E. Lamberg, P. Ogazón; official statement of decisions and recommendations made by Colonels Rafael del Valle and P. Ogazón. Notice from central government for all states to be on alert for disturbances. Statements by E. Lamberg, others, concerning military matters.
- (March, 1862) (Box 7, Folder 83)
  Notes from Plácido Vega to various officials and supporters, informing them of military developments. Copies of letters from Plácido Vega to P. Ogazón (reference to R. Meza, Corona, Alicia); to R. del Valle, Fortunato García (reference to ship Anáhauc); to Benito Juárez (matters relating to R. Meza); to Corona. Letters to Plácido Vega from J. Esquivel, M. Delgado, Fortino León (reference to ship Reforma); from M. Marquez, R. Félix y Buelna, E. Lamberg, Francisco de la Vega, (plans of Meza); from Fortino León, others. Copy of letter to R. Meza from Juan Sepúlveda telling of Meza's desire to include him in his plans. Reports by E. Lamberg, including inventories. Official instructions to be conveyed to R. del Valle, R. Corona, J. Sepúlveda concerning conspiracy of Meza. Statements by J. García Morales concerning deserters. Proclamation by Juárez concerning judicial proceedings. Statements by R. del Valle concerning prisoners, etc.
- (March-May, 1862) (Box 7, Folder 84)
  Military notes concerning Constitutional movement; letters to Plácido Vega from R. Felix y Buelna (restlessness among soldiers for want of pay, etc.); from Q. Douglas, P. Blancarte, I. Pesquiera (loyalty of individuals, military developments); from Eduardo Weber (changes in command within forces in state); from F. Tirado, concerning Esquivel; from R. del Valle (military plans); from Carlos Rivas, J.J.Tostado (financial matters); from J. Toledo, R. Corona, J. García Morales, Letters from Plácido Vega to R. Félix y Buelna, Q. Douglas (financial, other matters); to J. Mugarrieta (financial); to Carlos Rivas (military matters); to J.J.Tostado, J. García Morales, I. Pesquiera (military plans); to J.Toledo, R. Corona (reference to Márquez). Official statement concerning desertion of troops. Invoices showing amount owed by division for supplies. Official papers concerning lack of funds, changes in command; official report of action of R. Corona. Copy of statement by M. Márquez, setting forth latter's views, at variance with government in regard to Tovar. Official lists of deputies to national congress; statements by Corona, others, concerning execution of orders.
- (May, 1862) (Box 7, Folder 85)
  Letters to Plácido Vega from I. Pesquiera (financial matters); from Benito Juárez (surrender of Tovar; request for aid from Baja California; reference to French at Veracruz, to diplomatic break with France); from León Ángulo (uprising at Fuerte, other matters); from P. Ogazón (foreign intervention; threat of war; plans, steps to be taken against enemy, and (later) notice of outbreak of hostilities with France); from Isabal, I. Zaragoza (commentary on war); from J. Arzapalo, M. Doblado, R. Félix y Buelna, F. Tirado; from supporters, relatives. Copies of letters from Plácido Vega to Benito Juárez (military plans, changes in command); to León Ángulo, R. Corona, J. García Morales, I. Pesquiera (preparations for war with France); to J. Arzapalo, M. Doblado. Instructions to U. Lassepas. Financial statements concerning payment of sums owed. Charts showing number of men in battalion, quantities of arms, munitions possessed by artillery battalion.
- (June, 1862) (Box 7, Folder 86)
  Letters from Plácido Vega to Benito Juárez (sending of Corona to Alicia; reference to Tepic, to matters in northern states); to E, Lamberg, P. Ogazón (reference to ship Bayonnaise, to Tepic, to situation facing nation); to Jesus Vega, to various other military officers (instructions); to A. Aragón, P. Blancarte.
  Letters to Plácido Vega from J. García Morales (naval matters; French attempt to blockade port; reference to ship Mutine, etc.); from R. Corona (military matters); from E. Lamberg (financial matters; reference to Tepic, to other matters); from Isabal (military matters; reference to ship Bayonnaise, etc.); from C. Palomares, Antonio Vega, C. Peña, F. Cortés, E. Lamberg, J. Arzapalo, (political, military); from L. Tostado, P. Ogazón (reference to Corona, Tepic); from A. Angulo.
  Statement naming officers of artillery battalion; statement of debts owed; official military orders; chart of personnel. Reports by officers; inventories; financial reports.
- (July, 1862) (Box 7, Folder 87)
  Reports by Corona, others (account of Tepic, other matters). Instructions by Plácido Vega. Letters to Plácido Vega from I. Pesquiera (reference to financial crisis; request for military assistance; reference to ship Mutine and service rendered by captain; reference to ship República, etc.); from J. Pastori, consul at Liverpool; from Benito Juárez (suppression of Lozada and uprising); from R. Corona (reference to Alicia, to Tepic); from B. Silva, J. Cosío in Zacatecas.
  Letters from Plácido Vega to E. Conner (request for arms); to J. Pastori (account of matter involving French and Mexican ships Bayonnaise, Reforma, others; reference to Juan Kelly, etc.); to Benito Juárez (reference to naval affairs, to Tepic, to R. Meza and insurrection led by latter); to I. Comonfort (reference to naval matters, to Lozada, Tepic, etc.); to I. Zaragoza. Letters to Plácido Vega from F. Zarco, C. Palomares, Miguel Blanco, E. Lamberg, I. Zaragoza, J. González Ortega (Tepic); from R. Corona, I. Pesquiera (reference to Anáhauc, to affairs in Sonora); from others. Statement giving chronological sequence of events concerning ships Bayonnaise, República, Reforma, etc.
- (August, 1862) (Box 7, Folder 88)
  Letters to Plácido Vega from R. Corona (Tepic); from other military officers, officials; from J. Arzapalo, Q. Douglas, Benito Juarez (military plans; reference to Lozada, situation at Tepic, other matters); from J. García Morales (military matters); from J. González Ortega, I. Pesquiera. Letters from Plácido Vega to Camilo Vega, Antonio Vega, J. Arzapalo, Benito Juárez, J. García Morales, I. Pesquiera (military matters, plans); to J. González Ortega. List of deputies to national congress and alternates from Sinaloa. Copy of letter to Benito Juárez from J. González Ortega giving account of political and military matters, and views.
- (August, September, 1862) (Box 8, Folder 89)
  Letters to Plácido Vega from Manuel Hidalgo, J. Gonzalez Ortega (letter, dated September 13, tells of death of General Zaragoza; of González Ortega's appointment as Commander of the eastern division of the Federal army); from A. Aragón (military developments, plans, and differences with J. Arzapalo); from J. Arzapalo, concerning his personal enemies; from J. García Morales, E. Sánchez (conduct of Morales' men); from Benito Júarez (gratitude for information concerning Meza, Lozado, and supporters); from Jesús Vega (administrative matters); from I. Zaragoza (dated August, 1862); from other military officers, supporters. Letters from Plácido Vega to A. Aragón, E. Sánchez (conduct of soldiers); to J. García Morales, J. Arzapalo (instructions given by Plácido Vega to J. García Morales); to Benito Juárez (financial matters); to I. Pesquiera, J. González Ortega, B. Almada, P. Ogazón, Miguel Blanco, Minister of War, concerning Lozada, Tepic, French invasion; to Jesús Vega; to other military officers, officials (instructions). Report from Plácido Vega to J. González Ortega, I. Comonfort, I. Zaragoza (September 11), apprising them of state of affairs in Sinaloa.
- (September, October, 1862) (Box 8, Folder 90)
  Letters to Plácido Vega from J. Toledo, R. Corona, P. Blancarte, F. Cortés (financial matters); from Manuel Iriarte, J. Arzapalo (administrative matters); from Camilo Vega, Antonio Vega, Jesús Vega (military matters); from E. Lamberg (debts; claims of Captain Wilson); from J. García Morales, I. Pompa (personal interests of certain individuals in district). Letters from Plácido Vega to A. Aragón (discipline of troops); to J. Toledo, Benito Juárez (military movements in Sinaloa); to R. Corona (instructions); to P. Blancarte, F. Cortés, Manuel Iriarte, J. Arzapalo, Camilo Vega, Antonio Vega, C. Isabal, A. Blancarte, F. Tirado (mission of A. Ángulo); to E. Lamberg, P. Ogazón, J. García Morales, (reference to supplies from Arzapalo, military plans); to F. Zarco, concerning General Zaragoza; to other military officers, government officials. Bill for supplies bought for forces of J. García Morales; statements of receipt of goods by J. Arzapalo. Proclamation by Plácido Vega to inhabitants of Sinaloa concerning honors accorded postumously to General Zaragoza and to Degollado, Ocampo, and Valle.
- (November, 1862) (Box 8, Folder 91)
  Letters to Plácido Vega from I. Isabal (administrative, financial matters; reference to J. Kelly); from Miguel Figueroa, B. Insunza, M. Buelna, F. Tirado, A. Aragón, B. Peraza (administrative matters of prefect; conduct of J. Rojo); from Amado Blancarte; from J. Rojo (presentation of matters from latter's point of view; differences with B. Peraza); from Manuel Hernández (attack on Hacienda de Dolores); from local officials, supporters. Letters from Plácido Vega to I. Isabal, M. Figueroa, B. Insunza, M. Buelna, B. Peraza (instructions; reference to C. Palomares); to Benito Juárez (debts; cargo brought by sea); to local officials, supporters.
- (November, 1862) (Box 8, Folder 92)
  Letters to Plácido Vega from C. Palomares (March-October, 1862); from B. Silva, governor of Durango in absence of Patoni, on march to interior (August, 1862). Letter gives report of activities of Remedios Meza, who succeeded in obtaining military commission. Second letter from Silva asks Plácido Vega to use influence in capital to get Meza's commission revoked (October, 1862). Later letter thanks Plácido Vega for achieving satisfactory solution to matter. Letters to Plácido Vega from Richard Robertson; from E. Norton (October, 1862); from M. Iriarte, L. Angulo, I. Orrantia, M. Urrea (May-August, 1862); from Dr. Crepel. Letters to Plácido Vega from Camilo Vega, Jesús Vega (intelligence concerning activities among Indians of Crispín Tostado); from B. Insunza, A. Aragón. Letters from Plácido Vega to Crispín Palomares (November, 1862); to Jesús Vega (intentions of Arzapalo); to B. Insunza, A. Aragón, M. Urrea (November, 1862); to M. Iriarte (action of J. Arzapalo at hacienda).
- (December, 1862) (Box 8, Folder 93)